ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

SUMMARY

Program Manager and Data Scientist with ~8 years of proven success delivering on Objectives and Key business Results. Established and scaled enterprise—level Digital Transformation initiatives across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Enabled Data Science's 65% overall AI/ML market share across business functions within British Petroleum's US onshore O&G division (BPX) and independently produced \$997MM in value. Delivered \$500M+ in value annually via patent—pending AI—powered computational chemistry solutions for INFICON's Semiconductor business unit.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

November 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

British Petroleum (BP)

- · Acquired 45% of Exploration & Development's AI/ML market and enabled the team's 65% AI/ML market share across the organization directing and executing Data Science & ML Engineering Digital Transformation strategy.
- · Delivered all planned Q2 2024 Agile Features in Data Science and ML Engineering within the project scope.
- · Realized \$4MM in annual cost reductions prioritizing resources to build and deploy ML Sand Flowback prediction.
- · Coordinated stakeholder timelines and resources developing and launching ML Drilling AFE Cost prediction.

Product Owner

November 2023 – Present

British Petroleum (BP)

Denver, Colorado

- · Managed and productionalized the Long-term Production Risk Assessment app via Streamlit for Reservoir Engineering.
- · Oversaw the Azure cloud to AWS cloud Salt Water Disposal and Productivity Index report migration.

Senior Data Scientist

February 2023 – Present

British Petroleum (BP)

 $\stackrel{\circ}{Denver}$, Colorado

- · Generated \$977MM for the Permian Business Unit with a well development plan NPV of \$700MM, Drilling & Completions cost reductions of \$250MM, and core collection avoidance amounting to \$27MM productionalizing AI Lithofacies Prediction in Techlog, enabling regional fluid mobility assessments, and facilitating well development prioritization.
- · Drove \$20MM in annual value for Eagle Ford Reservoir Engineering and achieved a 500% increase in efficiency for well prospecting & assurance workflows launching ML Refracturing Production Forecasting via Streamlit.

Data Scientist

June 2018 – February 2023

INFICON

 $Syracuse,\ New\ York$

- · Directed \$500M+ in forecasted annual cost reductions and provisioned Neural Processing Units to support patent—pending Automated Sensor Calibration advances directly on next–generation semiconductor sensor technologies.
- · Led a 21% enhancement in Mass Spec signal fidelity (SciPy.optimize/Statsmodels), designed A/B Quality Control tests (SciPy.stats/Nolds) for all Mass Spec sensors, and documented mathematical foundations for proprietary algorithms.
- · Established 50% coverage across chemical detection and monitoring systems designing KPIs and executing A/B simulation tests via synthetic GC–MS data generated using PySwarms and SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate.
- · Achieved a 95% increase in density estimation accuracy inventing the Bijective Neural Architecture via PyTorch.

Research Assistant

June 2017 – August 2017

 $Syracuse\ University \mid Data\ Lab$

Syracuse, New York

· Modeled social media engagement metrics, formulating repeated measures experiments, utilizing Scikit-learn and NLTK.

Technology Analyst

June 2016 - August 2016

 $JPMorgan\ Chase\ \ \ Co.$

Jersey City, New Jersey

· Developed project business cases alongside senior team members and deployed code to live internal JPMC applications.

Software Engineer

 $June\ 2015-September\ 2015$

Self-employed

Syracuse, New York

· Engineered information retrieval systems for **British Petroleum** and local government clients as a subcontractor.

Undergraduate Research Assistant
Syracuse University | Hosein Research Group

August 2014 – May 2015

Syracuse, New York

· Awarded the **Dean's Leadership Grant** supporting simulation studies quantifying energy loss across solar cell surfaces.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors

USPTO Application 18/686,753

August 2023
Patent Pending

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing

BP Geophysics R&D Seminar

Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity

INFICON Data Analytics Summit

November 2020

Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches

Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session

April 2018

July 2024

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Core Analysis Workshop

UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology

April 2024/December 2023

Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX

Havens Consulting

April 2023

Machine Learning for Model Predictive Control & Process Analytics

Dr. S. Joe Qin, President of Lingnan University

June 2019

HONORS & AWARDS

Graduate Merit Scholarship

Syracuse University

August 2017 – May 2018

Summa Cum Laude

Syracuse University

May 2017

May 2017

The Warren Semon Prize Syracuse University

Dean's Leadership Grant

September 2014

Syracuse University

Dean's List

August 2014 – May 2017

Syracuse University

The Founders' Scholarship

August 2014 – May 2017

Syracuse University

EDUCATION

Syracuse University

May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University

May 2017

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science

Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Business Strategy, Business Development, Stakeholder Management, Agile Project Management, OKRs, CRISP-DM

Technical Artificial Intelligence, Deep Learning, Transfer Learning, Machine Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling,

Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Monte Carlo, Time Series, Statistical Signal Processing, Data Collection, Data Preprocessing, Data Analysis, Data Wrangling, Data Mining

Tools AWS SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Pandas, SciPy, Statsmodels, NumPy, NLTK,

Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog, Atlassian Jira, Azure DevOps